Finding Aid for Girls Friendly Society of the United States of America, Diocese of Michigan, records, 1896-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Girls Friendly Society of the United States of America, Diocese of Michigan, records 1896-1997
Girls Friendly Society of the United States of America. Diocese of Michigan.
1.5 linear foot
0451 Bk 2
The Girls Friendly Society of the United States of America, Diocese of Michigan serves girls and women within the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan. Their main function was to maintain several cottages, which were first used as vacation homes for working women in the 1890's and then slowly evolved into a summer camp for young girls. The record group includes meeting minutes, clippings, publications, and related materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records received from the Episcopal Diocese of Michigan through Cheryl Sands, Gordonwood Center (donor no. 1059 )
The record group is open to research.
The Detroit Branch of the Girls Friendly Society was started in 1895 when the organization first rented a cottage on Pine Lake to serve as a vacation house for working women. The society members emphasized organizing local fundraising events with the community and planning for the summer vacationers.
By the early 1900's the society owned three cottages and had transformed the property into a summer camp for young girls. In the 1950's the camp moved from Pine Lake to Ortonville and was renamed Camp Holiday. The society used the facilities year round, during the brief summer months it was a summer camp for young girls and for the rest of the year it served as a conference center. As Camp Holiday became the primary task of the society more resources went into the maintenance of the cottages and less time was spent connecting with the community through social events.
In the later 1970's the camp found itself financially strained. The society had altered the mission of the camp and no longer taught religious studies. The financial concerns and the lack of a strong mission forced a reorganization of the society in the 1980's when the Diocese of Michigan took over administration of the camp. The camp became co-ed and a strong Christian camp program was adopted. The camp continued to falter economically throughout the decade, membership slowly dwindled, and by the later half of the 1990's the society was considering disbanding.
The record group is divided into four series: Administration, Clippings, Photographic Prints, and Publications.
Subjects:
Girls Friendly Society of the United States of America. Diocese of Michigan.; Camps--Michigan.; Episcopal Church. Diocese of Michigan.; Girls--Michigan--Societies and clubs.; Women--Michigan--Societies and clubs.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Camps--Michigan.; Girls--Michigan.; Girls Friendly Society of the United States of America. Diocese of Michigan.; Pine Lake (West Bloomfield, Mich.); Prayer.; Women--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administration
  The bulk of the records are in the Administration series. This series is primarily composed of meeting minutes that span from 1896-1997. These meeting minutes reflect the evolving mission of the camp as it was influenced by the changing social norms. The meeting minutes comprise two groups, the House Committee and the Girls Friendly Society Board of Directors. These meeting minutes were kept intermingled because they had overlapping membership and in some instances the notes refer to one another. Interspersed throughout the meeting minutes are annual reports and monthly financial reports. These reports are kept with the meeting minutes because they are referenced in the meeting minutes. Significant issues found in the notes are the changing administration of the society and of Camp Holiday, the amount of resources spent on the maintenance of the cottages, and the annual experiences of the summer camp staff. The Administration series also contains information pertaining to the background of the camp, committee member lists, constitution and by-laws, brief correspondence which includes a letter sent to the Queen of England, material from a leaders workbook in 1980, membership policies, and the 1980 Trust Agreement.
  - Background Information (Box 1)
  - Certified Resolution of Change of Registered Office-Articles of Association 1953 (Box 1)
  - Committee Member List 1954-1988 (Box 1)
  - Construction and By-Laws-Revisions 1912-1998 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous 1923-1987 (Box 1)
  - Leader's Workbook Materials 1980 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Minutes 1896-1977 (Box 1)
    - 1896-1905 (Box 1)
    - 1909-1919 (Box 1)
    - 1920-1925 (Box 1)
    - 1926-1929 (Box 1)
    - 1930-1934 (Box 1)
    - 1935-1939 (Box 1)
    - 1940-1944 (Box 1)
    - 1945-1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1955-1956 (Box 1)
    - 1957-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1961 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - 1964 (Box 1)
    - 1965 (Box 1)
    - 1966 (Box 1)
    - 1967 (Box 1)
    - 1968 (Box 1)
    - 1969 (Box 1)
    - 1970 (Box 1)
    - 1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972 (Box 1)
    - 1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974 (Box 1)
    - 1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 1)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - 1982 (Box 2)
    - 1983 (Box 2)
    - 1984-1997 (Box 2)
  - Membership Policies (Box 2)
  - Trust Agreement 1980 (Box 2)
- Clippings
  Within the brief Clippings series are a few articles that describe the annual garden tour of Mrs. Ford's gardens organized by the Girls Friendly Society during the 1930's. There are also a few articles that provide more background knowledge of the society.
  - Garden Tour of Mrs. Henry Ford's Gardens 1935-1941 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1914-1984 (Box 2)
- Prints
  The Photographic Prints series is comprised of photographs that document the social activities the society organized with the young female members between 1940 and 1960. The pictures depict young girls dressed in costume for Halloween celebrations, picnics, and other social events. While some of the prints have captions, none of them include the names of the individuals in the photographs.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Social Activities 1948-1959 (Box 2)
- Publications
  The Publications series contains newsletters, pamphlets, a Girls Friendly Society magazine published in 1888, and a manual for House Committee members from 1954-1960. The majority of the pamphlets are an annual series that was used to publicize the Holiday House from 1903 to 1950. There are also a number of pamphlets that outline the revisions made to the constitution and the by-laws of the Girls Friendly Society between 1904 and 1963.
  - Magazine March 1888 (Box 2)
  - Manual, 'The Best if At Your Service' 1954-1960 (Box 2)
  - Newsletters
    - 'Highlights' 1952-1963 (Box 2)
    - 'Highlights' 1965 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets
    - Constitution and By-Laws 1904-1963 (Box 2)
    - 'History of the Girls Friendly Society in America' 1927 (Box 2)
    - Holiday House, Pine Lake, MI 1903-1920 (Box 2)
    - Holiday House, Pine Lake, MI 1921-1950 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1922-1961 (Box 2)